<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--and now:--><?oxygen RNGSchema="https://faustedition.uni-wuerzburg.de/xml/schema/faust-tei_neu.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[653]&lt;E&gt;</title>
                <author>zzm</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2018-07-05</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="doxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-07-12" who="krause">angelegt</change>
            <change when="2018-10-04" who="krause">überarbeitet, markiert</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="653"/>
            <div><head>Goethe’s House.</head>
            <p>An invitation to dinner at Madame de H——’s afforded me an opportunity of making the
                acquaintance of two of the Grand-duke’s principal ministers, or, as they are there
                called, Presidents of Colleges of Public Affairs, one of whom had had the singular
                good fortune of allying himself to the family of two of the most illustrious
                literary men in Germany, by marrying the daughter of Wieland, and, after her death,
                the daughter of Herder, his present lady. The dinner went off as all such ceremonies
                do in Germany among the grandees: it was a great deal too long: having begun at two,
                and ended at six o’clock; during which time, upwards of fifty dishes passed in
                successive review before us. In the evening, after the opera, I had the pleasure of
                being introduced to Madame S ——, the popular novel writer, who is meditating another
                of those light productions, which have gained her the reputation, all over Germany,
                of being the most desperate <hi rend="italic">bas bleu</hi> of her time. She is
                cheerful, agreeable, and <hi rend="italic">spirituelle,</hi> in her
                conversa<pb n="654"/>tion. <milestone unit="testimony" xml:id="bie3_6107" spanTo="#bie3_6107_end"/>On my return home, I found a kind note from Madame Goethe,
                intimating that her father-in-law would see me at half-past ten the following
                morning. There are forms which one must go through to see the great Patriarch. He
                likes not being taken by surprise; and whenever he has been so intruded upon, he has
                not appeared to advantage; has seemed confused, not much pleased, and niggard of his
                answers. He is, on the contrary, most amiable, all affability and playfulness, as
                when in his younger days, if visited by appointment. At his advanced age, which has
                now reached its eighty-first year, exposed to be stared at as a lion, and made
                frequently to pay the forfeit of his celebrity, by submitting to the impertinent
                intrusions of the idle and the curious, it is no matter of surprise that Goethe
                should appear to have some <hi rend="italic">bizarrerie</hi> in his manners.</p>
            <p>At half-past ten precisely, Goethe made his appearance in one of his classically
                decorated withdrawing rooms, into which I had been but the moment before introduced.
                He advanced towards me with the countenance of one who seems not to go through the
                ceremony of a first greeting <hi rend="italic">à contre cœur;</hi> and I felt
                thankful to him for that first impression on my mind. His person was erect, and
                denoted not the advance of age. His open and well-arched eyebrows, which give effect
                to the undimmed lustre of the most brilliant eye I have ever beheld, and his fresh
                look and mild expression of countenance, at once captivated my whole attention; but
                when he extended his friendly hand to welcome me to his dwelling, I stood absorbed
                in the contemplation of the first literary character of the age. The sound of his
                voice, which bespeaks peculiar affability, and the first questions he addressed to
                me respecting my journey, however, recalled me from my reverie, and I entered at
                once into the spirit which presided at the interview, alike free from frivolity and
                haughty reserve. I found him in his conversation ready, rather than fluent;
                following, rather than leading; unaffected, yet gentlemanly; earnest, yet
                entertaining; <pb n="655"/>and manifesting no desire to display how much he deserved the
                high reputation which not only Germany, but Europe in general, had simultaneously
                acknowledged to be his due. He conversed in French, and occasionally in English,
                particularly when desirous to make me understand the force of his observations on
                <rs>some recent translations of one or two of his works</rs> into that language. <rs>Faustus</rs> was
                one of these. The translation, by the present noble Secretary for Ireland, of that
                singular dramatic composition, which for beauty of style, and ingenuity of
                contrivance, leaves the old play of the same name by Marlowe far behind, seemed not
                to have given satisfaction to the veteran author. He observed to me, that most
                assuredly it was not a translation, but an imitation, of what he had written. “Whole
                sentences of the original,” added he, “have been omitted, and chasms left in the
                translation, where the most affecting passages should have been inserted to complete
                the picture. There were probably difficulties in the original which the noble
                translator might not be able to overcome; few foreigners, indeed, can boast of such
                mastery of our prodigal idiom, as to be able to convey its meaning with equal
                richness of expression, and strength of conception, in their own native language;
                but, in the case of the translation to which I allude, that excuse for imperfection
                does not exist in many of the parts which Lord Francis Gower has thought proper to
                omit. No doubt, the choice of expressions in the English translation, the
                versification, and talent displayed in what is <hi rend="italic">original
                    composition</hi> of his lordship’s own well-gifted mind, may be deserving of his
                countrymen’s applause; but it is as the author of Faustus <hi rend="italic">travesti,</hi> and not as <rs>the translator of Goethe’s Faustus</rs>, that the popular
                applause has been obtained.”</p>
            <p>The patriarch poet seemed far more satisfied with the translation of another of his
                beautiful dramas, the Tasso, by Mr. Charles Des Vœux. He said, “I understand
                Eng<pb n="656"/>lish <hi rend="italic">à ma manière,</hi> quite sufficiently to discover in
                that gentleman’s recent translation, that he has rendered all my ideas faithfully.
                    <hi rend="italic">Je me lisois moi-même dans la traduction.</hi> It is for the
                English to determine, if, in adhering faithfully to the ideas of the German
                original, Mr. Des Vœux <hi rend="italic">a conservé les règles et n’a pas trahi le
                    génie de sa langue. Je n’en suis pas juge: peut-être le trouvera-t-on un peu
                    trop Allemande.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text"><ref type="footnote">*</ref> Mr. Des Vœux has
                        since admitted, in a letter to me, the justice of Goethe’s remarks as to the
                        version of Tasso being “un peu trop Allemande;” but he also naturally
                        accounts for it, by the fact that he began and completed his task in
                        Germany, and at that time he had devoted himself exclusively to the reading
                        of German poetry. I am glad, however, to learn that a second edition is soon
                        to appear, free from many Germanisms, which cannot fail to give the English
                        reader as much satisfaction, as Goethe himself seems to have experienced in
                        the perusal of the first edition.</p></note></p>
            <p>The earliest and best translation from Goethe is William Taylor’s Iphigenia. This
                gentleman lives at Norwich, and being a provincial, his translation is not known as
                it deserves. The most famed translator of Goethe is Sir Walter Scott, who translated
                anonymously <hi rend="italic">Gotz von Berlichingen.</hi> One of the best jeux
                d’esprit published in the Anti-Jacobin is the <hi rend="italic">Rovers,</hi>
                generally ascribed to Mr. Canning. —This is a burlesque drama uniting the plots of
                Kotzebue’s Stranger and Goethe’s Stella. In Goethe’s play, the hero has two wives,
                and they agree to <hi rend="italic">share</hi> him between them. In Kotzebue’s, the
                hero takes back a runaway wife. The union of these plots affords matter for
                pleasantry. Of Goethe’s prose-works, “The Sorrows of Werter” is the most celebrated,
                though a very early production; but the “Letters from Switzerland,” a continuation
                of that famous novel, remain untranslated. “Wilhelm Meister” and the continuation
                have been translated by Carlyle. A third novel, “Elective Affinities,” ought to be
                translated as well as Goethe’s own life.</p>
            <pb n="657"/>
            <p>The conversation turning, by a natural transition, to the different methods of
                teaching modern languages, Goethe observed, that he could strongly recommend to my
                attention a mode of instructing effectually, as well as promptly, young people in
                any of the living languages, which was successfully adopted in the seminary for
                young Englishmen at Weimar, and by which the pupils were taught to think in, as well
                as to learn to read or write a foreign language. In that establishment, in which
                instruction in the German language is the principal object, the Director, Mr. A——,
                takes any English work which is most familiar to the students, and dictates to them
                whole passages from it in German, which, when completed, the students are to read
                aloud to the Director in English; by which method, he familiarizes them with the
                relative value and meaning of words in the two idioms, and gives them great facility
                of translation; and this the more so, as he will sometimes, when they are more
                advanced, dictate in German, from a well-known English book, whole passages, which
                he expects the students to write down immediately in English. As we were on the
                subject of education, an allusion was made, in the course of our conversation on the
                higher branches of instruction, to the different systems of moral philosophy which
                had at various times prevailed in Germany. I expressed a desire to know how Goethe,
                then in the vigour of life, and with an exalted mind, had comported himself towards
                the proselytes of Kant’s philosophy, during the prevalence of that system? Dr.
                Froriep, who is ever ready to supply that sort of information which is deduced from
                extensive reading, and who was present at the interview, observed, that when the
                system of transcendental metaphysics of the Königsberg philosopher had been nigh
                raising in Germany the same kind of popular effervescence which had marked the days
                of Luther, Goethe alone retained his wonted <hi rend="italic">sang-froid,</hi> and
                smiled at the warmth and indignation expressed against the new system by his
                <pb n="658"/>colleagues, Wieland and Herder. With that wisdom, which is so characteristic of
                his turn of mind, and a foresight worthy of his genius, he expressed an opinion,
                that the philosophy of Kant should be allowed to have its day, as all things have,
                and that all would be right again. He lives now to see the propriety of that
                opinion, and the fulfilment of his prediction.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text"><ref type="footnote">*</ref> I must not
                        omit to mention that in this country Mr. Wirgman, feeling a thorough
                        conviction of the excellence and solidity of the Kantesian Philosophy, has
                        been unremitting in his exertions to implant in England the knowledge of a
                        system, of the truth and value of which he is himself fully convinced. To
                        this end have the labours of this gentleman been incessant for the last
                        thirty years. He is the author of a series of articles in the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopœdia Londinensis,</hi> and is, I believe, at
                        present engaged in translating that celebrated work of Kant’s, “The Critic
                        of Pure Reason.”</p></note></p>
            <p>Throughout this interview, which lasted upwards of an hour, Goethe manifested great
                eagerness after general information, particularly respecting England and her
                numerous institutions; and also on the subject of St. Petersburgh, which he looked
                upon as a city that was fast rising to the rank of the first capital on the
                Continent, according to the opinion of many intelligent travellers, whom he had seen
                and conversed with on the subject. In taking leave of him, at length, Goethe put
                into my hands a small red morocco case, which he hoped I would accept as a <hi rend="italic">souvenir</hi> of our meeting; after which I withdrew, with
                sentiments of increased admiration for this celebrated man. The case contained two
                bronze medals, the one executed by Brandt of Berlin, the other by Bovy, and both
                represent the bust of the poet in bold relief, particularly the latter, which is
                decidedly of superior execution.<anchor xml:id="bie3_6107_end"/></p></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>