<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!--and now:--><?xml-model href="http://faustedition.net/schema/1.0/faust-tei.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://faustedition.net/schema/1.0/faust-tei.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[95]&lt;E&gt;</title>
                <author>T028</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2018-07-05</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="doxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-07-12" who="krause">angelegt</change>
            <change when="2018-10-05" who="krause">überarbeitet, markiert</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <pb n="95"/>
                <head>October 28.—</head>
                <p><milestone unit="testimony" spanTo="#bie3_4385_end" xml:id="bie3_4385"/>Prof.
                    Riemer, who is second librarian of the Public Library, called on us and amused
                    us above an hour, by describing Goethe’s mode of living, peculiarities,
                    etc.,—facts one cannot get in books, or from any source but the knowledge of an
                    intimate acquaint<pb n="96"/>ance. Prof. Riemer lived nine years in Goethe’s
                    house, and knew him, of course, from the lowest note to the top of his compass.
                    He said that Goethe is a much greater man than the world will ever know, because
                    he always needs excitement and collision to rouse him to exertion, and that it
                    is a great misfortune that he is now without such influence and example as when
                    Herder, Wieland, and Schiller were alive.</p>
                <p>I asked what had been his relations with those extraordinary men. He replied
                    that, from holding similar views in philosophy, Goethe and Schiller were nearest
                    to each other, and Herder and Wieland; but that after the deaths of Schiller and
                    Herder, Goethe became intimate with Wieland. Schiller, he said, had profited
                    much by his connexion with Goethe, and borrowed much from his genius,—among
                    other pieces, in his “William Tell,” which Goethe had earlier thought to have
                    made the subject of an epic poem; but now they are all dead, and since 1813
                    Goethe has been alone in the world.</p>
                <p>He has much on paper which has never been published, and much in his memory which
                    has not been put on paper, for he writes always by an amanuensis, to whom he
                    dictates from memoranda on a card or scrap of paper, as he walks up and down his
                    room. Of his views in physics and comparative anatomy, he has published little,
                    but a programme by a medical professor at Jena (Oken) has lately made a great
                    noise, in which the doctrine that the brain is formed from the <hi rend="italic">medulla spinalis</hi> was, no doubt, from hints first given by Goethe.</p>
                <p>Among the many unpublished things he has on hand, are parts of a <rs>continuation
                        of “Faust,”</rs> which Riemer had seen, in which the Devil brings Faust to
                    court and makes him a great man; and some poems in the Persian style and taste
                    which he wrote during the last war, to give a relief to his imagination and
                    feelings by employing himself on something that had no connexion with
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>He lives now, in his old age, in unconsoled solitude; sees almost nobody, and
                    rarely goes out. His enjoyment of life seems gone, his inclination for exertion
                    gone, and nothing remains to him, that I can see, but a very few years of cold
                    and unsatisfied retirement.<anchor xml:id="bie3_4385_end"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>